<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Leadership on Jens Rantil</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/tags/leadership/</link><description>Recent content in Leadership on Jens Rantil</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 08:06:01 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jensrantil.github.io/tags/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A one-on-one template</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/one-on-one-template/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 18:16:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/one-on-one-template/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have used the same &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Det7O1UQxIFgUywivldqTejmhyyeQ-YD1CNxXcGTPV0/edit?usp=sharing" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one-on-one template&lt;/a> with my last six managers, including other regular check-ins. I am very happy with it! A recent conversation with a friend made me realize I better share the template with the world. If nothing else, I should share it for my own sake - in case I need it again in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The template has given me a lot of structure to my one-on-ones which I previously never had. It has also guided my one-on-ones toward more actionable meetings, focusing on what needs to happen next.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Raise and Release</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/raise-and-release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 13:26:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/raise-and-release/</guid><description>&lt;p>Amazon&amp;rsquo;s founder Jeff Besos is famous for his &amp;ldquo;disagree and commit&amp;rdquo; management principle used in leadership. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disagree_and_commit" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to Wikipedia&lt;/a>, it means &amp;ldquo;that individuals are allowed to disagree while a decision is being made, but that once a decision has been made, everybody must commit to implementing the decision&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have a slight variation on this which I call &amp;ldquo;Raise and Release&amp;rdquo;, which happens &lt;em>before&lt;/em> a decision has been made. I use this principle particularly when someone proposes something I strongly disagree with &amp;ndash; or know will fail &amp;ndash; but for cases where I can&amp;rsquo;t affect the actual decision. Usually, it is for cases where I am &amp;ldquo;consulted&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;informed&amp;rdquo; in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Responsibility_assignment_matrix" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RACI&lt;/a> sense.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The hidden opportunity in feedback</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/the-hidden-opportunity-in-feedback/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 23:18:33 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/the-hidden-opportunity-in-feedback/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today I would like to talk about a missed opportunity when giving and receiving
feedback &amp;ndash; mainly the discussion that happens afterwards. A classical way to
give feedback is using the &lt;em>observed-perceived&lt;/em> method:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Describe the &lt;em>observed behavior&lt;/em> from your point of view. Do it as soon as
possible about the specific behavior that occurs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Describe the &lt;em>perceived impact&lt;/em> of the observed behavior.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, what commonly follows is that the receiver of the feedback
explains why the observed behavior was so &amp;ndash; followed by ending the feedback
session. &amp;ldquo;Thanks for your feedback, Jens! I did that because X, Y, &amp;amp; Z.&amp;rdquo;, then
walking away thinking&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>