<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Productivity on Jens Rantil</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in Productivity on Jens Rantil</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 23:37:08 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jensrantil.github.io/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I once almost burned out</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/burnout/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 19:45:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/burnout/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have been very close to burnout two times in my career. At the same employer.
Both times, the following held:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Tight deadline.&lt;/strong> I had an urgent project on my shoulders with a very very
tight deadline. In one of the cases, I also had a planned vacation starting
within a week - and I feared having to cancel the entire sailing trip with
my friends (it was my boat).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Low capacity.&lt;/strong> I had known the project was coming any day for weeks but
was unable to start working on it. As such, my mental and emotional capacity
was already strained.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>I was alone.&lt;/strong> I had no one to delegate to and was solely on my own. I was
the only person who knew the (DevOps) work that needed to be done. Despite
me flagging for 6-12 months that I needed to offload some responsibilities.
I felt helpless.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Constant nudging.&lt;/strong> The project was the highest priority project in the
company. Everyone kept asking me how it was going, requesting status
updates, or if they could help (they could not - see the previous bullet).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I &lt;strong>worked day and night&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Strictly speaking, I was not fully burned out; I was able to get out of bed, but
my entire body was shaking, I was unable to sleep, was annoyed, body
temperature was fluctuating between too hot &amp;amp; too cold, and I had anxiety.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Three Buckets of my time</title><link>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/three-buckets-of-my-time/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 23:50:03 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jensrantil.github.io/posts/three-buckets-of-my-time/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have a small framework for how I carve out my professional time. I think of
my working hours spent into three buckets:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teamwork (&amp;ldquo;team bucket&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Company-wide work (&amp;ldquo;company bucket&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My own initiatives (&amp;ldquo;me bucket&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s go through them one by one:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="teamwork-team-bucket">
 Teamwork (&amp;ldquo;team bucket&amp;rdquo;)
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#teamwork-team-bucket">
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading">&lt;/i>
 &lt;span class="sr-only">Link to heading&lt;/span>
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Time spent in the &amp;ldquo;teamwork&amp;rdquo; bucket is time I spend on tasks related to the
local team I am primarily working with. Usually these tasks are tied to issues
in a ticketing system, but it also includes team ceremonies (retros or planning
etc.).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>